Guide to the Frances Patai Oral Histories on Women Medical Volunteers in the Spanish Civil War ALBA.AUDIO.131
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Frances Patai Oral Histories on Women Medical Volunteers in the Spanish Civil War
1985-1992
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Patai, Frances
ALBA.AUDIO.131
0.8 Linear Feet in 1 card box and 1 box
36 audiocassettes
4 CDs
Frances Patai was an educator, writer, historian and feminist activist. Born in New York in 1930, she earned her bachelor's and master's degrees at the City College of New York in the 1950s and taught English and Communication courses throughout the City University of New York (CUNY) system. Patai was deeply concerned with human rights issues, in particular the rights and status of women, and in the last decade of her life she devoted her efforts to researching and writing a book on U.S. women medical personnel who volunteered during the Spanish Civil War. The oral histories that make up this collection are part of her extensive research material. The Frances Patai Oral Histories on Women Medical Volunteers in the Spanish Civil War consist of interviews with volunteers from the Spanish Civil War, primarily the women who served as nurses.
Biographical Note
Frances Patai was born on New York City's Lower East Side in 1930. As a teenager, she performed in Jewish resorts in the Catskills as an actress and dancer. In her twenties she attended classes at the City College of New York, earning her bachelor's degree in 1955 and her MA in 1957. Beginning in the 1970s she served as an English and Communications instructor at various institutions in the City University of New York (CUNY) system, including long-term appointments at John Jay College and the Borough of Manhattan Community Colleges.
Throughout her career Patai was concerned with the rights and status of women, addressing in a series of essays and articles issues related to rape, pornography, and abuse. During the 1980s she worked with the feminist organization Woman against Pornography, serving as spokesperson and organizing their annual WAP Awards, an event that promoted the non-sexist representation of women in advertising. In later life Patai turned her attention to the anti-fascist movements of the 1930s, and began to investigate the history of American volunteers who joined the Republican forces to fight against Franco's army during the Spanish Civil War. Patai focused her attention on the participation of American women volunteers in the Spanish Civil War, devoting her efforts to researching and writing a book on the contributions of nurses. Through her friendship with Fredericka Martin -- a nurse with the Medical Bureau to Aid Spanish Democracy who collected extensive biographical material on her former colleagues -- Patai gained access to unique primary materials, and to the surviving nurses themselves. She conducted these interviews over several years, as part of her research project. Patai died in 1998 before she could bring her project to fruition. She was 67 years old.
Related Material at the Tamiment Library/Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Fredericka Martin Papers (ALBA 001) Julia Newman: "Into the Fire" Research Files (ALBA 226) Frances Patai Papers (ALBA 131) Frances Patai Photographs (ALBA PHOTO 131) Frances Patai File in the Abraham Lincoln Brigade Archive (ALBA) Vertical Files: Individuals (ALBA VF 2)
Scope and Content Note
The Frances Patai Oral Histories on Women Medical Volunteers in the Spanish Civil War consist of 36 audiocassettes, which were separated from the Francis Patai Papers (ALBA 131). The interviews were conducted by Patai in the period 1985 to 1992, in the course of research for her book project on U.S. women medical personnel who vounteered during the Spanish Civil War. Most are with the women who volunteered as nurses, but also included are interviews with Abraham Lincoln Brigade veterans Moe Fishman and Steve Nelson, and with Marion Wachtel, widow of ALB volunteer Robert Merriman. Drafts of Patai's planned book, and her article "Heroines of the Good Fight: Testimonies of U.S. Volunteer Nurses in the Spanish Civil War, 1936-1939" (Nursing History Review, 3 (1995): 79-104), which utilizes the interviews in this collection, can be found in the Patai Papers (ALBA 131). Also included in the collection are tapes of a conference and a veterans' dinner, and a recording of Spanish Civil War songs.
Some transcripts of interviews in this collection can also be found in the Frances Patai Papers (ALBA 131).
Arrangement
Each recording has been assigned a unique item number (e.g., ALBA A 131-001), and the collection is arranged in alphabetical order by last name of the interviewee. (Women's maiden names, or names used during service in Spain, are listed first -- followed by names used later in life.)
Information on transcript location is included only under the first appearance of an interview subject in the collection.
Conditions Governing Access
Materials are open to researchers.
Audiovisual Access Policies and Procedures
Access CDs for some audiovisual materials in the collection are available by appointment for reading room viewing and listening only. Access to other audiovisual materials in this collection is available through digitized access copies. Researchers may view an item's original container, but the media themselves are not available for playback because of preservation concerns. Materials that have already been digitized are noted in the collection's finding aid and can be requested in our reading room.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
This collection came to New York University in January 2001 as part of the original acquisition of Abraham Lincoln Brigade Archives (ALBA) collections, formerly housed at Brandeis University. The accession numbers associated with this collection are 2001.209 and 2001.136.
Custodial History
The Frances Patai Oral Histories on Women Medical Volunteers in the Spanish Civil War were donated to Abraham Lincoln Brigade Archives by Frances Patai as part of the Frances Patai Papers in 1998. The collection came to New York University in January 2001 as part of the original acquisition of Abraham Lincoln Brigade Archives collections, formerly housed at Brandeis University.
Spain -- History -- Civil War, 1936-1939 -- Personal narratives.; Spain -- History -- Civil War, 1936-1939 -- Women.; Americans -- Spain -- History -- 20th century.; Spain -- History -- Civil War, 1936-1939 -- Participation, American -- Interviews.; Medical Bureau to Aid Spanish Democracy; Spain. Ejército Popular de la República. Abraham Lincoln Battalion; Medical Bureau and North American Committee to Aid Spanish Democracy; Martin, Fredericka I.
- Bell (Roberts), Hilda, 1991-01-15; cuid14393
  Existence and Location of Copies
  Transcript for this interview is available in Frances Patai Papers (ALBA 131), box 1, folder 3.
  - Access Copy (Box Shared Tamiment 124, Cd 001)
  - Original Recording (Box 1, Cassette 131-001)
- Bell (Roberts), Hilda; Mildred Rackley (Simon), 1991-01-14; cuid14394
  - Access Copy (1 of 2) (Box Shared Tamiment 124, Cd 002)
  - Access Copy (2 of 2) (Box Shared Tamiment 124, Cd 002)
  - Original Recording (Box 1, Cassette 131-002)
- Davidow, Ruth, 1992-01-20; cuid14395 (Box 1, Cassette 131-003)
  Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
  Format: 1/8" audiocassette, Duration: 94 minutes
  Transcript for this interview is available in Frances Patai Papers (ALBA 131), box 1, folder 7.
- Fisher, Ruth and Harry, 1988-05-21; cuid14396 (Box 1, Cassette 131-007)
  Format: 1/8" audiocassette, Duration: 48 minutes
- Fishman, Moe (Moses), 1989-11-06; cuid14397 (Box 1, Cassette 131-008)
  Format: 1/8" audiocassette, Duration: 43 minutes
- Freeman (Feinberg), Helen, 1990-04-20; cuid14398 (Box 1, Cassette 131-006)
  Format: 1/8" audiocassette, Duration: 34 minutes
- Goldin (Spiegel), Irene; Esther Brown, 1991-01-22; cuid14399 (Box 1, Cassette 131-034)
  Format: 1/8" audiocassette, Duration: 59 minutes
- Gonzala, Garcia Delgado, 1988-07-15; cuid14400 (Box 1, Cassette 131-009)
  Format: 1/8" audiocassette, Duration: 46 minutes
- Hill (Klein), Josephine, 1990-04-23; cuid14401 (Box 1, Cassette 131-013)
  Format: 1/8" audiocassette, Duration: 62 minutes
- Hill (Klein), Josephine, 1990-04-23; cuid14402 (Box 1, Cassette 131-014)
  Format: 1/8" audiocassette, Duration: 12 minutes
- Klavantz, Rae, July 1991; cuid14403 (Box 1, Cassette 131-015)
  Format: 1/8" audiocassette, Duration: 57 minutes
- Leight, Clara, 1986-12-17; cuid14404 (Box 1, Cassette 131-016)
  Format: 1/8" audiocassette, Duration: 90 minutes
  Notes and a partial summary for this interview is available in Frances Patai Papers (ALBA 131), box 3, folder 1.
- Leight, Clara, 1986-12-17; cuid14405 (Box 1, Cassette 131-017)
  Format: 1/8" audiocassette, Duration: 64 minutes
- Levine (Hartzman), May; Sidney Kaufman, 1991-01-27; cuid14406 (Box 1, Cassette 131-018)
  Scope and Contents
  On Side 2 of this tape, May Levine Hartzman and Sidney Kaufman are interviewed separately.
  Format: 1/8" audiocassette, Duration: 68 minutes
  Transcript for the May Levine (Hartzman) interview is available in Frances Patai Papers (ALBA 131), box 3, folder 2.
- Malbin, Virginia, 1985; cuid14407 (Box 1, Cassette 131-019)
  Preservation Note: "From beginning to 00:1:30, tape rewinds and repeats part of the conversation."
- Malbin, Virginia, 1991-01-25; cuid14408 (Box 1, Cassette 131-021)
- Malbin, Virginia; Esther Silverstein (Blanc), 1991-01-25; cuid14409 (Box 1, Cassette 131-020)
  Format: 1/8" audiocassette, Duration: 53 minutes
- Martin, Fredericka, undated; cuid14410
  - Access Copy (1 of 2) (Box Shared Tamiment 124, Cd 022)
  - Access Copy (2 of 2) (Box Shared Tamiment 124, Cd 022)
  - Original Recording (Box 1, Cassette 131-022)
- Martin, Fredericka, 1989-10-08; cuid14411
  - Access Copy (Box Shared Tamiment 124, Cd 023)
  - Original Recording (Box 1, Cassette 131-023)
- Merriman (Wachtel), Marion, 1991-02-03; cuid14412
  - Access Copy (Box Shared Tamiment 124, Cd 024.000001-2)
  - Original Recording (Box 1, Cassette 131-024)
- Nelson, Steve, 1991-04-19; cuid14413 (Box 1, Cassette 131-025)
  Format: 1/8" audiocassette, Duration: 95 minutes
- Nelson, Steve, 1991-04-19; cuid14414 (Box 1, Cassette 131-026)
  Format: 1/8" audiocassette, Duration: 6 minutes
- North (Green), Helen; Spanish Civil War Songs, 1987-05-08; cuid14415 (Box 1, Cassette 131-010)
  Notes and a partial summary for the Helen North (Green) interview is available in Frances Patai Papers (ALBA 131), box 3, folder 8.
- Rackley (Simon), Mildred, 1991-01-14; cuid14416 (Box 1, Cassette 131-032)
  Format: 1/8" audiocassette, Duration: 47 minutes
  The transcript for this interview is available in Frances Patai Papers (ALBA 131), box 3, folder 13.
- Rolfe, Mary, 1991-01-18; cuid14417 (Box 1, Cassette 131-027)
  Format: 1/8" audiocassette, Duration: 44 minutes
  The transcript for this interview is available in Frances Patai Papers (ALBA 131), box 3, folder 15.
- Seborer (Greenspan), Celia, 1987-02-21; cuid14418 (Box 1, Cassette 131-011)
- Seborer (Greenspan), Celia, 1992-05-15; cuid14419 (Box 1, Cassette 131-012)
  Format: 1/8" audiocassette, Duration: 52 minutes
- Sendor, Andrea (Sister Benedicta), 1990-05-15; cuid14420 (Box 1, Cassette 131-028)
- Schulman (Durem), Rebecca, 1991-01-26; cuid14421 (Box 1, Cassette 131-004)
  Notes and a partial summary for this interview is available in Frances Patai Papers (ALBA 131), box 4, folder 1.
- Schulman (Durem), Rebecca; Helen Freeman (Feinberg), 1991-01-27; cuid14422 (Box 1, Cassette 131-005)
  Format: 1/8" audiocassette, Duration: 70 minutes
- Shuldiner (Goldman), Anne, 1990-05-22; cuid14423 (Box 1, Cassette 131-029)
  Format: 1/8" audiocassette, Duration: 83 minutes
  Transcript for this interview is available in Frances Patai Papers (ALBA 131), box 4, folder 2.
- Silverstien (Blanc), Esther; Sana Goldblatt, 1991-01-17; cuid14424 (Box 1, Cassette 131-030)
  Notes and a partial summary for this interview is available in Frances Patai Papers (ALBA 131), box 4, folder 3.
- Silverstein (Blanc), Esther; Mary Rolfe, 1991-01-18; cuid14425 (Box 1, Cassette 131-031)
- Temple, Lenora, 1986-12-13; cuid14426 (Box 1, Cassette 131-035)
  Format: 1/8" audiocassette, Duration: 92 minutes
- Spanish Civil War Conference, 1988-03-19; cuid14427 (Box 1, Cassette 131-033)
  Format: 1/8" audiocassette, Duration: 54 minutes
- VALB: 55th Anniversary Dinner, 1992-04-26; cuid14428 (Box 1, Cassette 131-036)
  Format: 1/8" audiocassette, Duration: 25 min.